<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_jtei.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_jtei.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="jTEI">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Intuitively representing the nature of text: the TAG model for
               text</title>
            <author>
               <name>
                  <forename>Elli</forename>
                  <surname>Bleeker</surname>
               </name>
               <name><forename>Ronald</forename><surname>Haentjens Dekker</surname></name>
               <name><forename>Bram</forename><surname>Buitendijk</surname></name>
               <affiliation>The authors are part of the R&amp;D group of the Humanities Cluster of
                  the Royal Dutch Academy for Arts and Sciences.</affiliation>
               <email>elli.bleeker@gmail.com</email>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>TEI Consortium</publisher>
            <date/>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>For this publication a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International license
                     has been granted by the author(s) who retain full copyright.</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>No source, born digital.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Revues.org -centre for open electronic publishing- is the platform for journals in
               the humanities and social sciences, open to quality periodicals looking to publish
               full-text articles online.</p>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en">en</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords xml:lang="en">
               <term>markup</term>
               <term>digital editing</term>
               <term>genetic criticism</term>
               <term>text modeling</term>
               <term>overlap</term>
               <term>data models for text</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change/>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <div type="abstract" xml:id="abstract">
            <p>Over the past decades, the question of <mentioned>what text really is</mentioned> has
               been addressed by a large number of conferences, workshops, articles, and blog posts.
               If there is one thing that, taken together, those contributions illustrate, it is
               that our understanding of text is – and has been – constantly in flux and open for
               many interpretations. This flexible and heterogeneous understanding of text is
               reflected by the TEI Guidelines: users can mix modules and elements in order to come
               to their encoding model of choice. As a result, most encoding models are based on a
               scholar conceptual understanding of a text and their research interest in a text.
               Still, there often are significant gaps between how a scholar conceptually thinks
               about text, how this translates to an encoding model, and how a computer understands
               the encoded text. Put differently: how an encoding looks to a human reader often
               differs from the way that information is stored on a computer.</p>
            <p>In the present contribution, we illustrate how the Text-As-Graph (TAG) hypergraph
               data model and the associated syntax TAGML can be employed to express and store
               textual features in a way that corresponds more closely with the scholar’s
               understanding of it. TAG’s functional design is based on the objective to reconcile
               the conceptual model, the encoding model and the informational model. The
               expressiveness of the syntax TAGML allows scholars to digitally represent their
               understanding of a text in a more explicit and formal manner. This information is
               then stored in the hypergraph data model for text. Consequently, a TAGML processor
               will not require any application layer in order for the text to be processed,
               queried, and analysed as it is intended and understood by the encoder. Finally, TAG’s
               approach will also promote the sustainability, archivability, and reuse of the text
               encoding.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>

         <div xml:id="intro">
            <head>Introduction</head>
            <p>Over the past decades, the question of <mentioned>what text really is</mentioned> has
               been addressed by a large number of conferences, workshops, articles, and blog posts.
               If there is one thing that, taken together, those contributions illustrate, it is
               that our understanding of text is – and has been – constantly in flux and open for
               many interpretations. This flexible and heterogeneous understanding of text is
               reflected by the TEI Guidelines: users can mix modules and elements in order to come
               to their encoding model of choice. As a result, most encoding models are based on a
               scholar conceptual understanding of a text and their research interest in a text.
               Still, there often are significant gaps between how a scholar conceptually thinks
               about text, how this translates to an encoding model, and how a computer understands
               the encoded text. Put differently: how an encoding looks to a human reader often
               differs from the way that information is stored on a computer.</p>
            <p>A clear example of this lack of congruence is seen with what we call <term
                  xml:id="nonlinear">non-linear text</term>, a textual phenomenon often present on
               historical or literary documents in the form of deletions and additions. We consider
               text to be non-linear when there is more than one order in which words or characters
               may be placed without influencing the semantics of the text. A straightforward
               example is the sentence <eg>This is a <hi rend="strike-out">first</hi>
                  <hi rend="addition">second</hi> attempt.</eg> From the perspective of a human
               reader, the deleted and the added word represent two readings of the character
               sequence. The deleted and the added word are located at the same position in the text
               sequence and they are mutually exclusive: reading from left to right, the sentence
               either says <eg>this is a first attempt</eg> or <eg>this is a second attempt</eg>. We
               say that the text characters are <term>fully ordered</term> until the point where the
               variation occurs (at the crossed-out word <q>first</q>). At this point, the text
               characters are <term>unordered</term>. The two reading paths converge again after the
               variation ends, so the text characters are again fully ordered after the addition. We
               therefore also call non-linear text <term>partially ordered text</term>.</p>
            <p>From an informational perspective, however, the partially-orderedness as perceived by
               a human reader is not represented as such in the underlying data model. In TEI XML,
               partially ordered text may be encoded like this: <egXML
                  xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><s>This is a
                        <del>first</del><add>second</add> attempt.</s></egXML> As human readers, we
               assume that if the <gi>del</gi> and <gi>add</gi> elements were to be placed in a
               different order, they would not have the same meaning (see <ref type="bibl"
                  target="#dekk2017">Haentjens Dekker and Birnbaum</ref>and <ref type="bibl"
                  target="#dekk2018">Haentjens Dekker et al.</ref>). However, in XML, all text and
               markup are typically ordered.<note>Only XML attributes and XML attribute values are
                  unordered.</note> In order for an XML processor to understand that the markup
               element <gi>subst</gi> expresses the start of partially ordered text, it needs to
               have access to an application layer like a schema that explains the semantic meaning
               of the markup tag. The more responsibility is delegated to additional application
               layers, the more complex the processing of the XML document becomes.<note>See also
                     <ref type="bibl" xml:id="quoteref1" target="#sper2008">Sperberg-McQueen and
                     Huitfeldt</ref>, who point out that any mechanisms defined by the TEI to
                  express textual features like discontinuity are not understood or supported by
                  generic XML tools; <quote source="#quoteref1">they require vocabulary-specific
                     support by a different layer of code</quote>, and by <ref target="#per2009"
                     type="bibl" xml:id="quoteref2">Peroni and Vitali</ref> who state that a TEI XML
                  document with specific markup that requires to be <quote source="#quoteref2"
                     >understood and exploited by a very specific and application-dependent
                     tool</quote> defeats the purpose of switching to XML in the first place. This
                  line of reasoning reflects the software development principle of Separation of
                  Concerns, which sets out to decrease complexity, promote sustainable development,
                  and facilitate the maintenance of code.</note> Ideally, therefore, one likes to
               avoid depending on the application layer(s) for TEI XML documents to be processed in
               accordance with a scholar’s expectations. That means information about non-linearity
               and other alternative text structures or orderings should be part of the data model
               and not the application layer(s). Once a data model is able to represent and store as
               many properties of a text as possible, the application layer(s) do(es) not need to
               supplement the model and can focus on actual application-level tasks instead (<ref
                  type="bibl" target="#dekk2017">Haentjens Dekker and Birnnaum</ref>).</p>
            <p>In the present contribution, we illustrate this line of reasoning argument with the
                  <ref target="https://huygensing.github.io/TAG/">Text-As-Graph (TAG)</ref>
               hypergraph data model and the associated syntax <ref
                  target="https://github.com/HuygensING/TAG/tree/master/TAGML">TAGML</ref>. Both TAG
               and TAGML are designed to express and store textual features in a way that
               corresponds more closely with the scholar’s understanding of it. TAG’s functional
               design is based on the objective to reconcile the conceptual model, the encoding
               model and the informational model. The expressiveness of the syntax TAGML allows
               scholars to digitally represent their understanding of a text in a more explicit and
               formal manner. This information is then stored in the hypergraph data model for text.
               Consequently, a TAGML processor will not require any application layer in order for
               the text to be processed, queried, and analysed as it is intended and understood by
               the encoder. Finally, TAG’s approach will also promote the sustainability,
               archivability, and reuse of the text encoding. </p>
            <p>The textual examples used in this article come from modern manuscripts (i.e.,
               authorial holographs and drafts dating from the late nineteenth, early twentieth
               century) that are encoded from a genetic perspective on text, meaning that the
               encoder is interested in capturing the various textual revisions in great detail.
               This interest, combined with the type of manuscript material, presents the encoder
               with textual features that are notoriously complex to model in TEI XML: overlapping
               text structures, discontinuous text, and non-linear text are more rule than
               exception. After a brief description of the research objectives of the field followed
               by an illustration of three textual features, the article goes on to describe the
               main characteristics of the TAG model. The third and final section of the article
               addresses the theoretical and practical implications of using TAGML to express the
               example texts from the first section. By contrasting the TAG model with the TEI XML
               model, the article illustrates how a text encoded in TAGML is understood and
               processed in a way that is closer to the genetic scholar’s understanding of the text.
               <!-- add: nice concluding sentence - how wonderful is it all --></p>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="genetic-research">
            <head>Textual Genetic Research and Text Modeling</head>
            <div xml:id="objectives">
               <head>Research Objectives</head>
               <p>The field of textual genetic research is concerned with the way literary texts
                  originate and develop over time. To this end, draft manuscripts provide a great
                  source of information as the writings on these documents often reflect the
                  author’s train of thought: words are crossed out, sentences are added, paragraphs
                  transposed… In other words, draft manuscripts represent traces of a writing
                  process and by extension the creation and development of a literary work. Since
                  that’s exactly what textual genetic scholars intend to capture and study, it’s
                  important that information related to the writing process is expressed as detailed
                  as possible. Additionally, textual genetic editors set out to store and represent
                  the results of their research in such a way, that it can be explored by others.
                  This may be in a digital research environment or a digital scholarly
                     edition.<note>Examples of digital research environments and editions
                     specifically aimed at supporting and presenting textual genetic research
                     include the <ref target="https://www.beckettarchive.org/">Beckett Digital
                        Manuscript Project</ref> (created by Dirk van Hulle and Vincent Neyt,
                     ongoing); the <ref target="http://research.cch.kcl.ac.uk/proust_prototype/"
                        >prototype</ref> of an opening from a notebook of Marcel Proust (created by
                     Julie André and Elena Pierazzo); the <ref target="http://faustedition.net/"
                        >genetic edition</ref> of Johann Wolfgang Goethe’s <title>Faust</title>
                     (edited by Anne Bohnenkamp et al); the <ref
                        target="https://www.beckettarchive.org/ads/Ads.htm">electronic edition</ref>
                     of Willem Elsschot’s <title>Achter de Schermen</title> (edited by De Bruin et
                     al, 2007); and the <ref target="https://rotunda.upress.virginia.edu/melville/"
                        >Fluid Text edition</ref> of Herman Melville’s <title>Typee</title> (edited
                     by John Bryant, 2006). All links were last accessed on <date when="2020-02-25"
                        >February 25, 2020</date> in a Mozilla Firefox browser.</note></p>
               <p>In order to adequately represent and study a text’s genesis, editors typically (1)
                  express textual variation within one text; (2) map the relationships between texts
                  and documents related to the genesis of a text; and (3) compare textual variation
                  across documents; i.e., textual collation.<note>It’s not within the scope of this
                     article to survey describe this workflow in more detail, or to survey the
                     digital tools that support the activities within this scholarly
                     workflow.</note> A tool used to support either of these activities needs to
                  recognise the kind of information that is relevant for textual genesis and –
                  ideally – also ensure that this information is retained throughout the processing.
                  For example: if a tool ignores or discards the information about an author’s
                  revision process because it isn’t able to recognise the way this information is
                  encoded, it will have serious consequences for the analysis of the text’s genesis.
                  Incidentally, although we use examples from textual genetic studies throughout
                  this article, it may be noted that this principle applies to a wide variety of
                  text encoding and text processing.</p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="features">
               <head>Complex Textual Features</head>
               <p>Occurrences of non-linear text structures are many and various and can get very
                  complex very fast. For reasons of clarity and brevity, the following paragraphs
                  discuss three simple examples of complex textual structures. For more complex
                  cases, see <!-- add link to appendix? Or maybe on the TAGML website? -->. Unless
                  indicated otherwise, the examples come from the authorial holograph of <title>To
                     the Lighthouse</title> by <ref type="bibl" target="#woolf1927">Virginia
                     Woolf</ref>.</p>
               <div xml:id="nonlinearity">
                  <head>Non-linearity</head>
                  <p>As mentioned <ref target="#nonlinear">above</ref>, we understand non-linear
                     text as having multiple paths through a text: a sequence of words or characters
                     that splits into two or more branches, for instance at the point where
                     variation in the text occurs that join together again at the end of the
                     variation. The encoder can use markup in order to mark the location of the
                        <term>branching</term> of the text. The three figures below present cases of
                     non-linearity:</p>
                  <div xml:id="deletion">
                     <head>Single Deletion or Addition</head>
                     <p>In this example, the words <q>impossible barriers</q> are striked through by
                        the author. This means that there are at least two variant states of the
                        text, one including the deletion and one excluding it: <q>difference of
                           opinion, impossible barriers, prejudices</q> or <q>difference of opinion,
                           prejudices</q>.<figure xml:id="single_deletion">
                           <graphic url="img/single_deletion.png" width="620px" height="980px"/>
                           <head type="legend">A single deletion. Fol. 27; SD p. 13.</head>
                           <head type="license"/>
                        </figure></p>
                  </div>
                  <div xml:id="immediate-del">
                     <head>Immediate Deletion</head>
                     <p>An immediate revision, also called by its latin term <term>currente
                           calamo</term>, means that the revision is made during the first spell of
                        writing (and not when the author later returns to the text to make
                        corrections). The example in <ref target="immediate_del">figure 2</ref>
                        shows how Woolf started the sentence with the word <q>This</q> and
                        immediately corrected it to <q>The</q>. This means that there is no other
                        way of reading the text; no variant state that does not include the
                        revision, simply one path: <q>This The idea has grown...</q><figure
                           xml:id="immediate_del">
                           <graphic url="img/immediate_del.png" width="620px" height="980px"/>
                           <head type="legend">An immediate deletion. Fol. 7; SD p. 3; Names to be
                              used.</head>
                           <head type="license"/>
                        </figure></p>
                  </div>
                  <div xml:id="grouped-rev">
                     <head>Grouped Revision</head>
                     <p>We already saw an example of a grouped revision in the introduction; <ref
                           target="grouped_rev">figure 3</ref> represents another case: <q>for being
                           so certainly disagreeable</q>. The grouped revision is very similar to
                        the single deletion and the single addition: again, there are two ways of
                        reading the text, one including the word that has been deleted, and one
                        without that word and including the addition. However, in the case of a
                        grouped revision, scholars encode that the deletion and the addition belong
                        together semantically. In TEI XML this can be indicated by grouping them
                        with the <gi>subst</gi> element (see also the example in the introduction).
                        Conceptually, this implies that the order of the contents of the
                           <gi>subst</gi> element are placed is temporarily irrelevant. The two
                        words – <q>so</q> and <q>certainly</q> – alternate and are mutually
                        exclusive: whether we choose the original reading so or the corrected
                        reading certainly, they are at the same distance from the beginning of the
                           sentence.<figure xml:id="grouped_rev">
                           <graphic url="img/grouped_rev.png" width="680px" height="980px"/>
                           <head type="legend">A grouped revision. Fol. 13; SD p. 6.</head>
                           <head type="license"/>
                        </figure></p>
                  </div>
                  <div xml:id="other-cases">
                     <head>Other Cases of Nonlinearity</head>
                     <p>Note that in the examples so far, the branching of the text occurs on the
                        original source manuscript; markup is used to flag the start and end of the
                        nonlinearity. However, there are also cases in which an encoder would like
                        to represent nonlinear information that is not on the original source
                        document. The TEI markup elements <gi>app</gi> and <gi>choice</gi>, for
                        instance, have a similar effect of partially ordered information: they group
                        together <quote source="#quoteref3">a number of alternative encodings for
                           the same point in a text</quote> (<ref type="bibl" xml:id="quoteref3"
                           target="#TEI2019">TEI P5, chapter 3.4</ref>. As a consequence,he contents
                        of the <gi>choice</gi> element are placed have no influence on the semantic
                        meaning. <!-- TODO: voorbeeld toevoegen --></p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div xml:id="Discontinuity">
                  <head>Discontinuity</head>
                  <p>Discontinuity happens when a text forms semantically a single continuous
                     utterance, but is interrupted by other elements. The example in figure 4 is
                     taken from a question on the TEI-L <!-- REF toevoegen -->and presents an
                     interesting case in which a narrator (Marion) cites a letter she has received.
                     She intersperses this citation, however, with her own comments upon the text of
                     the letter (<q>wrote Ada</q> and <q>I had told them
                     so</q>).<!-- Noot: Ik wil hier graag een tekstgenetisch voorbeeld van geven, zoals een "del" 
                        die betrekking heeft op meerdere maar niet alle woorden in een zin. Ik ken dit uit Anne Frank 
                        maar ben nog op zoek naar voorbeelden uit andere documenten. 
                        Tot ik die heb gevonden gebruik ik dit voorbeeld. -->
                     Ideally, the citation is encoded as one single expression instead of three
                     separate expressions. <figure xml:id="discontinuity1">
                        <graphic url="img/discontinuity1.png" width="680px" height="980px"/>
                        <head type="legend">An example of discontinuity in a running text (<ref
                              target="#Watanna1916" type="bibl">Watanna 1916, p.171</ref>)</head>
                        <head type="license"/>
                     </figure></p>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>

      <back>
         <div type="bibliography">

            <listBibl>
               <bibl xml:id="dekk2017"><author>Haentjens Dekker, Ronald</author> and <author>David
                     J. Birnbaum</author>. <date>2017</date>. <title level="a">It’s More Than Just
                     Overlap: Text As Graph</title><title level="m">Proceedings of Balisage: The
                     Markup Conference 2017</title><series>Balisage Series on Markup
                     Technologies</series>, <biblScope unit="volume"
                     >19</biblScope><date>2017</date><idno>https://doi.org/10.4242/BalisageVol19.Dekker01</idno></bibl>

               <bibl xml:id="dekk2018"><author>Haentjens Dekker, Ronald</author>, <author>Elli
                     Bleeker</author>, <author>Bram Buitendijk</author>, <author>Astrid
                     Kulsdom</author> and <author>David J. Birnbaum</author>. <date>2018</date>.
                     <title level="a">TAGML: a Markup Language of Many Dimensions</title><title
                     level="m">Proceedings of Balisage: The Markup Conference 2018</title>.
                     <series>Balisage Series on Markup Technologies</series>, <biblScope
                     unit="volume"
                     >21</biblScope><idno>https://doi.org/10.4242/BalisageVol21.HaentjensDekker01</idno></bibl>

               <bibl xml:id="sper2008"><author>Sperberg-McQueen, Michael C.M.</author> and
                     <author>Claus Huitfeldt</author>. <date>2008</date>
                  <title level="a">Markup Discontinued. Discontinuity in TexMecs, GODDAG Structures,
                     and Rabbit/Duck Grammars</title><title level="m">Proceedings of Balisage: The
                     Markup Conference 2008</title>. <series>Balisage Series on Markup
                     Technologies</series>, <biblScope unit="volume"
                     >1</biblScope><idno>https://doi.org/10.4242/BalisageVol1.Sperberg-McQueen01</idno></bibl>

               <bibl xml:id="per2009"><author>Peroni, Sylvio</author> and <author>Fabio
                     Vitali</author>. <date>2009</date>. <title>Annotations with EARMARK for
                     Arbitrary, Overlapping and Out-of-Order Markup</title>. <title level="m"
                     >Proceedings of the 2009 ACM Symposium on Document Engineering</title>.
                     <idno>﻿10.1145/1600193.1600232</idno></bibl>

               <bibl xml:id="woolf1927"><author>Woolf, Virginia</author>. <date>1927</date>.
                     <title>To the Lighthouse</title>, Holograph ms. Berg Collection, New York
                  Public Library. <editor>Pamela L. Caughie</editor>, <editor>Nick Hayward</editor>,
                     <editor>Mark Hussey</editor>, <editor>Peter Shillingsburg</editor>, and
                     <editor>George K. Thiruvathukal</editor><ref
                     target="http://www.woolfonline.com">Woolf Online</ref>.</bibl>

               <bibl xml:id="TEI2019">TEI Consortium. <date>2013</date>. <title>TEI P5: Guidelines
                     for Electronic Text Encoding and Interchange</title>. Version 2.5.0. Last
                  updated July 26. N.p.: <ref
                     target="http://www.tei-c.org/Vault/P5/2.5.0/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/">TEI
                     Consortium</ref>.</bibl>

               <bibl xml:id="Watanna1916"><author>Watanna, Onoto</author>. <date>1916</date>.
                     <title>Marion, the Story of an Artist’s Model</title>. <pubPlace>New
                     York</pubPlace>: <publisher>W.J. Watt</publisher>.
                     <idno>urn:oclc:record:1048793515</idno>.</bibl>
            </listBibl>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
